<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cherrytree>
  <node unique_id="26" master_id="0" name="Exploitation" prog_lang="custom-colors" tags="" readonly="0" nosearch_me="0" nosearch_ch="0" custom_icon_id="0" is_bold="0" foreground="" ts_creation="1743256549" ts_lastsave="1743256980">
    <rich_text>
</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h1">Exploitation</rich_text>
    <rich_text>


During the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Exploitation</rich_text>
    <rich_text> stage, we look for ways that  these weaknesses can be adapted to our use case to obtain the desired  
role (i.e., a foothold, escalated privileges, etc.). If we want to get a  reverse shell, we need to modify the PoC to execute the code, 
so the  target system connects back to us over (ideally) an encrypted connection  to an IP address we specify. 
Therefore, the preparation of an exploit  is mainly part of the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Exploitation</rich_text>
    <rich_text> stage.



These stages should not be strictly separated from each other, as  they are closely connected. Nevertheless, it is still important to  distinguish which 
phase we are in and its purpose. Because later, with  much more complex processes and much more information, it is very easy  to lose track of the 
steps that have been taken, especially if the  penetration test lasts several weeks and covers a massive scope.




</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h2">Prioritization of Possible Attacks</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

Once we have found one or two vulnerabilities during the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Vulnerability Assessment</rich_text>
    <rich_text>  stage that we can apply to our target network/system, 
we can prioritize  those attacks. Which of those attacks we prioritize higher than the  others depends on the following factors:
		• Probability of Success
		• Complexity
		• Probability of Damage

First, we need to assess the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">probability of successfully</rich_text>
    <rich_text> executing a particular attack against the target. </rich_text>
    <rich_text link="webs https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln-metrics/cvss">CVSS Scoring</rich_text>
    <rich_text> can help us here, using the </rich_text>
    <rich_text link="webs https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln-metrics/cvss/v3-calculator">NVD calculator</rich_text>
    <rich_text> better to calculate the specific attacks and their probability of success.


</rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Complexity</rich_text>
    <rich_text> represents the effort of exploiting a  specific vulnerability. This is used to estimate how much time, effort,  
and research is required to execute the attack on the system  successfully. Our experience plays an important role here 
because if we  are to carry out an attack that we have never used before, this will  logically require much more research 
and effort since we must understand  the attack and the exploit structure in detail before applying it.

Estimating the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">probability of damage</rich_text>
    <rich_text> caused by the  execution of an exploit plays a critical role, as we must avoid any  damage to the 
target systems. Generally, we do not perform DoS attacks  unless our client requires them. Nevertheless, attacking the running  services live 
with exploits that can cause damage to the software or the  operating system is something that we must avoid at all times.

In addition, we can assign these factors to a personal point system  which will allow the evaluation to be more accurately calculated based  on our skills and knowledge:


</rich_text>
    <encoded_png char_offset="476" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="fb6cb7276bdbde2f729f9b3dd78acebb7c33b82f1b348ebfff3c567bb5f44492"/>
    <encoded_png char_offset="2555" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="2cd91aff472de3726431de9ae0d37f6995f8b5b71f4b82231048f89a7bfc0259"/>
  </node>
</cherrytree>
