<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cherrytree>
  <node unique_id="19" master_id="0" name="Common Pitfalls" prog_lang="custom-colors" tags="" readonly="0" nosearch_me="0" nosearch_ch="0" custom_icon_id="0" is_bold="0" foreground="" ts_creation="1742990198" ts_lastsave="1742990700">
    <rich_text>
</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h1">Common Pitfalls</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

While performing penetration tests or attacking HTB boxes/labs, we  may make many common mistakes that will hamper our progress.  In this  section, we will discuss some of these common pitfalls and how to  overcome them.



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h2">VPN Issues</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

We may sometimes face issues related to VPN connections to the HTB  labs network.  First, we should ensure that we are indeed connected to  the HTB network.


</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">Still Connected to VPN</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

The easiest method of checking if we have successfully connected to the VPN network is by checking whether we have </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Initialization Sequence Completed</rich_text>
    <rich_text> at the end of our VPN connection messages:

</rich_text>
    <rich_text justification="left"></rich_text>
    <rich_text>



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">Getting VPN Address</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

Another way of checking whether we are connected to the VPN network is by checking our VPN </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">tun0</rich_text>
    <rich_text> address, which we can find with the following command:

</rich_text>
    <rich_text justification="left"></rich_text>
    <rich_text>

As long we get our IP back, then we should be connected to the VPN network.



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">Checking Routing Table</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

Another way to check for connectivity is to use the command </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">sudo netstat -rn</rich_text>
    <rich_text> to view our routing table:

</rich_text>
    <rich_text justification="left"></rich_text>
    <rich_text>



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">Pinging Gateway</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

From here, we can see that we are connected to the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">10.10.14.0/23</rich_text>
    <rich_text> network on the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">tun0</rich_text>
    <rich_text> adapter and have access to the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">10.129.0.0/16</rich_text>
    <rich_text> network and can ping the gateway </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">10.10.14.1</rich_text>
    <rich_text> to confirm access.

</rich_text>
    <rich_text justification="left"></rich_text>
    <rich_text>

Finally, we can either attack an assigned target host on the 10.129.0.0/16 network or begin enumeration for live hosts.



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">Working on Two Devices</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

The HTB VPN cannot be connected to more than one device  simultaneously. If we are connected on one device and try to connect  from another device, the second connection attempt will fail.

For example, this can happen when our VPN connection is connected in  our PwnBox, and then we try to connect to it from our Parrot VM at the  same time. Alternatively, perhaps we are connected on our Parrot VM, and  then we want to switch to a Windows VM to test something.



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">Checking Region</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

If we feel a noticeable lag in our VPN connection, such as latency in  pings or ssh connections, we should ensure that we are connected to the  most appropriate region.
HTB provides VPN servers worldwide, in </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Europe</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">USA</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Australia</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, and </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Singapore</rich_text>
    <rich_text>. Ideally, it would help if we tried to connect to the server closest to us to get the best possible connection.

To change our VPN Server, go to </rich_text>
    <rich_text link="webs https://app.hackthebox.eu/home">HackTheBox</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, click on the top-right icon that says </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Lab Access</rich_text>
    <rich_text> or </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Offline</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, click on </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Labs</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, and then click on </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">OpenVPN</rich_text>
    <rich_text>. Once we do, we should be able to pick our VPN server location and pick any of the servers within that region:
</rich_text>
    <rich_text justification="left"></rich_text>
    <rich_text>



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">VPN Troubleshooting</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

In case we face any technical issues when connecting to the VPN, we  can find detailed guidance on troubleshooting VPN connections on this </rich_text>
    <rich_text link="webs https://help.hackthebox.eu/troubleshooting/v2-vpn-connection-troubleshooting">HackTheBox Help page</rich_text>
    <rich_text>.



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h2">Burp Suite Proxy Issues</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

</rich_text>
    <rich_text link="webs https://portswigger.net/burp/communitydownload">Burp Suite</rich_text>
    <rich_text>  is a crucial tool during web application penetration tests (as well as  other assessment types). Burp Suite is a web application proxy and can  cause a few issues on our systems.


</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h4">Not Disabling Proxy</rich_text>
    <rich_text>

When we turn the Burp proxy in our browser, Burp will start to  capture our traffic and intercept our requests. This will make it stop  any requests we make in the browser, i.e., visiting a page until we go  to Burp, examine the request, and forward the request.

A common pitfall is forgetting to turn off the browser proxy after  closing Burp, so it keeps intercepting our requests. If this happens, we  will see that our browser is not loading any pages, 
so we should check  if the browser proxy is still on. We can do that by clicking on the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Foxy Proxy</rich_text>
    <rich_text> plugin icon in </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Firefox</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, and making sure it's set to </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Turn Off</rich_text>
    <rich_text>:



If we are not using a plugin like </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">Foxy Proxy</rich_text>
    <rich_text>, we can  check the browser's connection settings and make sure the proxy is  turned off. Once we do, we should be able to continue browsing without  any issues.



</rich_text>
    <rich_text scale="h2">Changing SSH Key and Password</rich_text>
    <rich_text>


In case we start facing some issues with connecting to SSH servers or  connecting to our machine from a remote server, we may want to renew or  change our SSH key and password to make sure they are not causing any  issues. We can do this with the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">ssh-keygen</rich_text>
    <rich_text> command, as follows:


By default, SSH keys are stored in the </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">.ssh</rich_text>
    <rich_text> folder within our home folder (for example, </rich_text>
    <rich_text family="monospace">/home/htb-student/.ssh</rich_text>
    <rich_text>).   If we wanted to create an ssh key in a different directory, 
we could  enter an absolute path for the key when prompted. We can encrypt our SSH  key with a password when prompted or keep it empty if we do not want to  use a password.

</rich_text>
    <encoded_png char_offset="630" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="98c8524cf4931edf4510dcbf7d7738ea8522bbb2887cae3c74cf97672cf8cbbc"/>
    <encoded_png char_offset="808" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="a21898e8772a76d2ca26eb940e8649d1feca572e2e3969639aad9dfafb5d61ec"/>
    <encoded_png char_offset="1019" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="e2b4df08b965a7ae716c6d0760e72a634935912e5eda3b04b1ece99cc42a151d"/>
    <encoded_png char_offset="1235" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="98fbcb13ea4b2e8d678bfd9193e2460aa9f06987ef0f7f445dff27f0821f44fd"/>
    <encoded_png char_offset="2485" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="cab3c3d038749f63fbd497343e8e1b300fba737f2e69703704a71f44ae61836d"/>
    <encoded_png char_offset="3535" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="fced6a9fd0d3fb162ea1c568a0b69b14749938ed69a350f82fdca05f55459e73"/>
    <encoded_png char_offset="4058" justification="left" link="" sha256sum="3f7554cd20a58726611d4526067e09218211c961b63a752d8e4e76ef483121ec"/>
  </node>
</cherrytree>
